<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document>
    <properties>
        <title>Creating new provider with Maven</title>
        <author email="pawel.rubach@sorcersoft.com">Paweł Rubach</author>
    </properties>
    <body>
        <h1 id="Creating_new_provider_with_Maven">Creating new provider with Maven</h1>
        <h2 id="Prerequisites">Prerequisites</h2>
        <ul>
            <li>Java 1.6</li>
            <li>Maven 3.0</li>
            <li>Eclipse with m2e (maven) plugin</li>
            <li>Sorcer distribution</li>
            <li>(before official Sorcer release) Maven settings.xml updated for Sorcer</li>
        </ul>
        <h2 id="Creating_the_project_.28archetype_version_1.0.0-alfa-3.29">Creating the project (archetype version
            1.0.0-alfa-3)
        </h2>
        <p>
            <ol>
            <li>Go to directory which will be the parent of your new project</li>
            <li>Call maven to use the archetype
                <pre>mvn archetype:generate -DarchetypeGroupId=org.sorcersoft.sorcer -DarchetypeArtifactId=sorcer-provider</pre>
                or
                <pre>mvn archetype:generate -Dfilter=org.sorcersoft.sorcer:</pre>
            </li>
            <li>Answer questions:</li>
            <ol>
                <li>groupId: This will usually be your organization's reversed domain name, e.g. com.sorcersoft</li>
                <li>artifactId: The project name and the project directory name, e.g. myprovider</li>
                <li>package: The Java package for your provider classes, by default groupId is used</li>
                <li>serviceDescription: The description of your provider. The given description can be seen in the Sorcer Service Browser.</li>
                <li>providerInterface: The Java interface name of your provider (service type) that will be exposed to requestors</li>
                <li>providerClass: The name of the class that will implement the provider interface</li>
                <li>serviceName: The name of your service</li>
            </ol>
            <li>Confirm properties configuration
                <p>Now you can accept or modify entered inputs, including the default ones. If everything is OK,
                    press Y.
                </p>
            </li>
            <li>Import your maven projects to your IDE (IntelliJ Idea or eclipse, for example). Below you can find information on
                how to import your project to IntelliJ idea</li>
            <li>You can remove the (service UI) &lt;artifactId&gt;-sui module unless you are going to create a graphical user
                interface attached to your provider. You can also remove the &lt;artifactId&gt;-proxy module unless you want
                to crate a custom provider proxy. Remember to delete the corresponding &lt;module&gt; entry in your provider
                pom.xml for any removed module from your provider project.
            </li>
                <li>To build your project in your the top-level directory of your project execute:
                    <pre>mvn install</pre>
                </li>
            </ol>
        </p>
        <h2 id="Using_IDE">Choosing your Integrated Development Environment (IDE)</h2>
        <p>
            For the development of Sorcer service providers you can choose any Java IDE that supports Apache Maven 3.x,
            however, we suggest that you use one of the following ones:
            <ul>
                <li>Eclipse 4.x - please refer to <a href="using-eclipse.html">this manual</a> to see how to import a Sorcer Service Provider project
                into Eclipse.</li>
                <li>IntelliJ Idea - below you can find a screenshot and a short instruction on how to import a Sorcer
                Service Provider project into IntelliJ Idea</li>
            </ul>
        </p>

        <h2 id="Importing_provider">Importing project into IntelliJ Idea</h2>
        <p>
	  To work with Sorcer the free community edition of <a href="http://www.jetbrains.com/idea/">IntelliJ Idea</a> should be sufficient.
           <ol>
               <li>Open IntelliJ Idea</li>
               <li>Select import project and point the top-level directory of your provider project as in Figure below</li>
               <img src="new-provider/importToIdea.png"/>
               <li>In the next steps of the importing wizard you can leave the defaults and continue</li>
               <li>When the project is imported you can use the "Maven Projects" window to build the project</li>
           </ol>
        </p>

        <h2 id="Starting_provider">Starting provider</h2>
        <p>
            <ol>
                <li>Start Sorcer - please refer to our <a href="getting-started.html">Getting Started Guide</a> to see how to do that</li>
                <li>Start provider (from console in project directory):
                    <pre>ant -f &lt;serviceName&gt;-prv/boot.xml</pre>
                </li>
                <li>If you use IntelliJ Idea you can drag and drop the boot.xml script to the "Ant build" window and double-click the "boot.provider" goal</li>
            </ol>
        </p>
        <h2 id="Testing_provider">Testing provider</h2>
        <p><ul>
            <li>To test your provider start sample requestor (client):
            <pre>ant -f &lt;serviceName&gt;-req/run.xml</pre>
            </li>
            <li>If you use IntelliJ Idea you can drag and drop the run.xml script to the "Ant build" window and double-click the "run.requestor" goal</li>
            </ul>
        </p>
    </body>
</document>